Finding Aid for Jasper Francis Cropsey visual materials, 1855-1856
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jasper Francis Cropsey visual materials 1855-1856
Cropsey, Jasper Francis, 1823-1900.
92117 Aa 1 UAm UAs
Sketch book of scenes along the St. Lawrence River and the University of Michigan campus.
1 volumes
2 painting
1 drawings
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The sketchbook was donated in 1937 by Mrs. Max Winkler (donor no. 130 ) who had received it as a gift. The paintings and drawing were donated to the university in 1890 by Andrew Dickson White.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Artist commissioned by the Board of Regents to paint the campus and the observatory of University of Michigan.
Sketchbook, 1855-1856 The original of the sketchbook is located in the library vault; the use copy (photocopies) is located in Aa/1 Cropsey. A master negative microfilm of the sketchbook is available for staff use only.
The Cropsey paintings include The University of Michigan campus, 1855 and The Detroit Observatory of the University of Michigan, 1855. Originals of both are on display in the library director's office. Digital files scanned from copy negatives are available online.
The Cropsey drawing is a pencil sketch of The University of Michigan campus, 1855.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Art.; Artists.; Detroit Observatory.; Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.); Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); President's House (University of Michigan); Saint Lawrence River.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus--1855.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Paintings.
- Sketchbook
  The Cropsey sketch book includes several studies done for his commissioned works at the university as well as other sketches of the Ann Arbor area. It also contains sketches made on his travel by steamer through the Great Lakes and St. Lawrence River, including stops in Montreal and at Niagara Falls. The contents of the sketch book are listed by page/item number. Blank pages are included in the list.
  - Front cover
  - Notes inside front cover., 1.
  - "J. F. Cropsey. New York.", 2.
  - Beginning of sketch of ship?, 3.
  - Ship., 4.
  - "Cumulus sky on Lake Erie September 12, 1855. From on board Steamer Plymouth Rock.", 5,6.
    (2 pages)
  - "View of the Huron at Ann Arbor, Michigan., 7,8.
    na 4722
  - Blank., 9.
  - "Rev. Dr. Tappan's House at Ann Arbor. Michigan University.", 10.
  - Blank., 11.
  - Details of the University of Michigan campus, with notes., 12.
  - Blank., 13.
  - Landscape., 14.
  - Blank., 15.
  - Two details of ships., 16.
  - Lake scene with notes., 17.
  - "Thousand Isles, St. Lawrence, on Steamer New York at Sunrise 18 September 1855.", 18.
  - Blank., 19.
  - "Steamer stoped [sic] at the town." With notes on the island, 20.
  - "Looking down the St. Lawrence.", 21.
  - "On the St. Lawrence.", 22.
  - Blank., 23.
  - "Looking over the St. Lawrence from Montreal.", 24.
  - "Montreal. September 20th 1855 from the [Quebec?] ferry", 25, 26.
    (2 pages. na 8952)
  - A roof top?, 27.
  - "Montmorency Falls, 21st Sept.", 28.
  - [Undescribed], 29.
  - "Plains of Abraham. September 21st.", 30.
  - Sketch of boat., "Monument to Wolf." With notes.; 31.
  - "From [Swords?] Hotel. Quebec. September 22nd.", 32.
  - "Quebec Wharf. September 22nd 1855" and "Camels Hump from Essex Junction. September 24th 1855.", 33.
  - Detail of tree trunk and stump, and small sketch of skyline, 34.
  - Landscape of Mt. LaFayette?, 35.
  - "Mt. LaFayette., September 25th, 1855.", 36.
  - Blank., 37.
  - "Hemlock stump. Birch log. September 25th." With notes., 38.
  - Blank., 39.
  - Trees and rocks September 25th., 40.
  - Sketch of Eagle Cliff?, 41.
  - "Eagle Cliff", 42.
  - "Looking from Bethlehem, toward Mt. Washington. September 26th 1855" with an additional sketch of tree., 43,44
  - Sketch of mountain scene., 45.
  - Sketch of a rocky cliff. With notes., 46.
  - Notes on Mt. Washington., 47.
  - Sketch of rocks., 48.
  - "White Notch" 2 pages., 49,50
  - Blank., 51.
  - "Willey Mountain from the Willey House." With notes., 52.
  - Blank., 53.
  - "Elm tree. Conway Valley", 54.
  - Mt. Washington and the Sago River", 55,56
  - Small sketch of woman. With notes on colors., 57.
  - Sketch of pine trees., 58.
  - Blank., 59.
  - Two small sketches of figures in doorway., 60.
  - Blank., 61.
  - View of cabin, bridge and trees., 62.
  - Blank., 63.
  - Sheep., 64.
  - Blank., 65.
  - Sheep., 66.
  - Blank., 67.
  - Sheep., 68.
  - Sketches of Chocorua Peak?, 69.
  - "Chocorua Peak", 70.
  - Blank., 71.
  - "Birches at Tamworth", 72.
  - Sketch of plant with notes, October 8, 1855., 73, 74
  - Blank., 75.
  - Elms at Tamworth., 76.
  - "Note to above" (Under Table Rock?], 77.
  - "Under the Table rock Niagara falls, March 20, 1856.", 78.
  - "N[iagara?] Falls", 79.
    (Upside down in volume)
  - Forest scene., 80.
  - Sketch of mountain scene?, 81.
  - Rocks and water., 82.
  - Blank., 83.
  - "Goldenrod and Immortal", 84.
  - "At Niagara Falls.", 85.
  - Barn, wagon and house., 86.
  - Blank., 87.
  - "Mt. Jefferson from Glen House.", 88.
  - "From the Glen House. Sunrise. October [6?] 1855", 89,90
    (copy negative #na 8953)
  - "1/2 hour before Sunrise, at North Conway. October 7, 1855.", 91.
  - Mill and waterfall., 92.
  - "Sky at Niagara Falls, March 20, 1856.", 93.
  - "Mist at Niagara Falls.", 94.
  - "Sky over the Catskill Mt. Hudson Rv. R.R. March 22nd, 185[6?]", 95,96
    (With notes. 2 pages)
  - "Sky in Catskill Mt. H.R.R.R. March 22nd, 1856", 97.
  - Blank., 98.
  - Blank., 99.
  - Blank., 100.
  - Blank., 101.
  - "Conway October 7th." Notes on trees, 102.
  - Landscape., 103,104.; 2 pages
  - "Morning of October 16th 1855 at the Catskill Mt. House.", 105,106.
    (With notes. 2 pages.)
  - "Notes to [Trenton] Falls. August 29th 1855", 107,108.
    (Upside down in volume, 2 pages)
  - "Note to Trenton Falls", 109,110.
  - Lake, ship and trees., 111.
  - "Lindon. Note to Niagara.", 112.
  - Blank., 113.
  - Notes inside back cover., 114.
- Paintings
  - The Detroit Observatory of the University of Michigan, 1855, oil on paper
    (Original located in director's office.)
  - The University of Michigan Campus, 1855, oil on paper
    (Commissioned by the university's first president, Henry Philip Tappan. The university is seen from the northeast, from near the modern Forest Hill Cemetery.)
    (Original located in director's office)
- Drawings
  - The University of Michigan Campus, 1855, pencil sketch (Folder UAm)